Finding Aid for Edward N. Hartwick Papers, 1898-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward N. Hartwick Papers 1898-1978, 1940-1960
Hartwick, Edward N.
3 linear feet
85199 Aa 2
President of the Wayne County Republican Precinct Organization and member of the 14th Congressional District Republican Committee; files relating to political activities; also photographs, motion pictures, and sound recordings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the fit of Mrs. Louis Hartwick (Donor no. 5892 ) and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1976.
The collection is open to research.
Edward N. Hartwick was active in Michigan Republican Party politics in the 1940s and 1950s. He served as president of the Wayne County Republican Precinct Organization, a reform group created to oppose "boss" control of the local party structure. He was also a member of the 14th Congressional District Republican Committee and a delegate to National Republican Conventions, most notably in 1952.
The papers of Edward N. Hartwick center around his involvement in the Republican party in the Wayne County area, and on the state and national level. The series in the collection are Wayne County Republican Party Activities; State Republican Central Committee; Election of 1952; Miscellaneous Political Files; Personal; Visual Materials; and Sound Recordings.
Included in the collection are meeting minutes, party organizational materials, and other materials relating to his activities within the Wayne County party organization and the Michigan State Central Committee. In addition, there are papers dealing with Hartwick's role as a delegate to the 1952 Republican National Convention. He received many letters urging him to support the various candidates - Eisenhower, MacArthur, and Taft.
Subjects:
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Republican Party (Mich.). 14th Congressional District Republican Committee.; Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Republican Party (Mich.). Wayne County Republican Precinct Organization.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Au Sable River (Mich.); Brake, D. Hale, 1891-1979; Cleary, Owen J., 1900-1960.; Hartwick, Edward N.; Hartwick family.; Hartwick Pines State Park (Mich.); King, Charles.; Martin, John Butlin, 1909-; Millard, Frank G. (Frank Gurnee), 1897-1976.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Parks--Michigan.; Political elections--1952.; Political elections--1956.; Political elections--1960.; Prison riots.; Reid, Neil E., 1871-; Republican Party (Mich.); State Prison of Southern Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Hartwick, Edward N.; Civil rights movements--United States.; Communism--United States.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Labor movement--United States--Political activity.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Republican Party (Mich.)
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Ayres, William H. (William Hanes), 1916-; Curtis, Carl T. (Carl Thomas), 1905-2000; Feikens, John, 1917-2011; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998.; Humphrey, George M. (George Magoffin), b. 1890.; Lipscomb, Glenard Paul, 1915-; Mitchell, James Paul, 1900-1964.; Morrow, E. Frederic (Everett Frederic), 1909-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Stassen, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1907-2001; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Wayne County Republican Party Activities
  - Wayne County Republican Precinct Organization
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Organization undated, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Board of directors undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1940-1956 (Box 1)
    - Minute Book 1941-1949 (Box 1)
    - Contributors 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Finance undated, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - 14th Congressional district Republican Committee
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Candidates for delegate to district convention
      - 1946 (Box 1)
      - 1948 (Box 1)
      - 1952 (Box 1)
      - 1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Convention platform 1949 (Box 1)
    - Section book 1953 (Box 1)
    - Finances undated, 1946-1956 (Box 1)
    - Minutes undated (Box 1)
    - Newsletter 1958 (Box 1)
    - Precinct delegate election results 1948 (Box 1)
    - Alternates to Republican State Convention September 1, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Republican Campaign Committee of Wayne County minutes 1952 (Box 1)
  - Wayne County Republican "five and ten" club undated (Box 1)
    (plan for organization and operation)
  - Lists of registered voters, Grosse Pointe area
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1950-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
- State Republican Central Committee
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Campaign organization (Box 1)
  - Officers 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Republican County Chairman's manual (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning effects of redistricting on Congressional results undated (Box 1)
  - Campaign 1956 (Box 1)
  - Campaign 1962 (Box 1)
- Election of 1952e>
  - "The Michigan Republican delegation of 1952" 1952 by James W. Miller (Box 2)
  - National Republican Convention
    - Papers 1952 (Box 2)
    - Delegate Contact Operation 1952 (Box 2)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower campaign 1952
    - Telegrams in support of presidential nomination (Box 2)
    - Letters in support of presidential nomination, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - The National Delegate, from Americans for Eisenhower (Box 2)
    - Campaign literature (Box 2)
  - Douglas MacArthur, campaign 1952
    - Letters in support of presidential nomination (Box 2)
    - Campaign literature (Box 2)
  - Reginald B. Naugle 1952 campaign literature (Box 2)
  - Robert A. Taft, campaign 1952
    - Letters in support of presidential nomination, sampled, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Campaign literature (Box 2)
  - "A program for Republican victory in 1952" undated (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Political Files
  - 15th Congressional district 1937 minutes (Box 2)
  - Campaign organization literature undated, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Cobo for Governor Club 1956 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence undated, 1935-1950 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1951-1964 (Box 2)
  - Cuyahoga County plan undated (Box 2)
  - Election workers, papers concerning roles 1946-1955 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Citizenship project volunteers 1964 lists (Box 2)
  - Los Angeles Republican Party
    - Los Angeles plan 1952-1959 (Box 2)
    - "Our need a businesslike approach," 1959 by the Republican Associates of Los Angeles (Box 2)
  - National Republican Convention delegates 1940, 1944 (Box 2)
  - "Organizing the rural vote," 1955 by James P. Bigley (Box 2)
  - Public housing statement undated (Box 2)
  - Republican Citizens Committee (Box 2)
  - "Truman, the Republicans, and 1948" 1945 by Claude Robinson (Box 2)
  - Young Republican National Convention 1955 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings 1958, 1964 (Box 2)
- Personal
  Within the Personal series, there are materials relating to the presentation of the Edward E. Hartwick Pines Park to the State of Michigan by Mrs. Karen B. Hartwick in 1927. There are also some personal papers, mainly correspondence, of Edward Edgar Hartwick (1871-1918), the father of Edward N. Hartwick, and a family tree.
  - Personal papers 1898, 1918, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Hartwick Pines: Correspondence, Dedication material and miscellanea 1927, 1935, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Hartwick-Michelson Family Tree (Box 2)
- Visual Material
  - Photographs, 3 folders
    - Edward E. Hartwick Pines, Grayling (Box 2)
    - Family (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous photos with University of Michigan Alumni, Robert Candor, Robert Taft, and others (Box 2)
  - Motion Pictures, 6 reels
    - ''Michigan's Century of Progress," 1960, b&w (Box 3)
      (history of Michigan under Republican rule)
    - "The Truth Behind the Jackson Prison Riot,", b&w (Box 3)
    - Richard Nixon train tour of Michigan 1956, 2 reels; color, silent (Box 3)
    - 1952 campaign
      (3 segments on 1 reel)
      - Republican National Convention 1952, b&w (Box 3)
      - Eisenhower in Saginaw, Michigan 1952, color (Box 3)
      - Eisenhower Inaugural, b&w, color (Box 3)
    - Republican Candidates for State Office 1952, b&w
      (6 films in 1 canister)
      - D. Hale Brake, State Treasurer (Box 3)
      - Owen J. Cleary, Secretary of State (Box 3)
      - Charles King, Justice State Supreme Court (Box 3)
      - John B. Martin, Jr., Auditor General (Box 3)
      - Frank G. Millard, Attorney General (Box 3)
      - Neil F. Reid, Justice, State Supreme Court (Box 3)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound Recording series includes recordings of Republican speakers, including Carl Curtis, Barry Goldwater, George M. Humphrey, Richard M. Nixon, Harold Stassen, and Arthur Summerfield. Topics discussed include Republican politics, blacks and the struggle for civil rights, the investigation of communists in the United States, and the dispute over trade union campaign contributions.
  - Tapes 1-2
    - Address of Arthur Summerfield, Postmaster General, Detroit Economic Club. Ca. 1954 also discussion by unidentified man (J.B. Matthews?) concerning "red menace" in Illinois, double track; 7 in.; 3 3/4 ips and 7 1/2 ips (Box 3)
  - Tape 3
    - Meeting at Alger War Memorial to review February 19th State Convention, February 28, 195?, Double track: 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 4
    - Side 1: Address of Harold Stassen, Lincoln Day Dinner, 15th Congressional District, Detroit February 9, 1954, Double track: 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
    - Side 2: Address of Congressman William Ayres, Lincoln Day Dinner, 14th Congressional District; also talk by John Feikens February 10, 1954, Double track: 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 5
    - Side 1: Address of Congressman Glenard Paul Lipscomb, 16th Congressional District Dinner February 13, 1954, Double track: 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
    - Side 2: Address of Richard Nixon, Homer Ferguson Dinner April 3, 1954, Double track: 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 6
    - Address of Secretary of Labor, James Mitchell, Flint, Michigan February 23, 1954, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
      (recorded by National Broadcasting Company)
  - Tape 7
    - Address of E. Frederic Morrow, entitled, "Can Any Good Came Out of Washington?" September 30, 1955, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 8
    - Address of Richard Nixon at the Young Republican Convention, Detroit June 17, 1955, 3 3/4 ips; 5 in. (Box 3)
      (recording of radio broadcast)
  - Tape 9
    - Discussion of Carl Curtis, Barry Goldwater, and rank and file union men talking about the campaign contributions made by unions in Michigan for Democratic candidates December 15, 1955, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 10
    - Address of E. Frederic Morrow, administrative officer, special projects division at the White House; Detroit, Mich., Dwight Eisenhower Birthday celebration. Talk concerns civil rights struggle January 20, 1956, 10 minutes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tapes 11-12
    - 14th Congressional District Republican Campaign Strategy Conference March 10, 1956, 2 tapes; double track; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)
  - Tape 13
    - Address of Secretary of the Treasury, George M. Humphrey, Detroit Economic Club October 8, 1956, 3 tapes; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 3)